<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="kde_overlay_shell_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2026 Xaver Hugl

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
    OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
    THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Overlay on top of other windows">
    This protocol allows the client to create "overlay" surfaces that are
    on top of xdg_toplevel windows of other clients.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the
    testing phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with
    the corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes
    can only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="kde_overlay_shell_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="overlay shell global">
      This interface is used to create overlay surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the overlay shell manager object">
        Destroys the manager object. Objects created by this manager are
        not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_overlay_surface">
      <description summary="create an overlay surface">
        Creates an overlay surface attached to the toplevel described by
        the toplevel handle.

        If the toplevel still exists when the request is processed, the
        compositor will respond with a configure event on the overlay
        surface.

        If the toplevel doesn't exist when this request is processed, the
        compositor will immediately send the kde_overlay_surface_v1.closed
        event on the newly created object.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="kde_overlay_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="xdg_toplevel_handle" type="string"
           summary="toplevel handle exported by xdg_foreign_unstable_v2"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="role" value="0"
        summary="given wl_surface already has a role"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="kde_overlay_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="overlay surface">
      When this object is created, the compositor immediately sends either
      the closed event, or a configure event.
      The client must wait for the first configure event and ack it before
      it may attach the first buffer.

      The client may attach a null buffer to the surface at any time to hide
      the overlay, and commit a non-null buffer again to show it again.
      TODO add a request_configure for this case, so it definitely matches the
      latest desired size?
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the overlay surface">
        This informs the compositor that the lock surface object will no
        longer be used.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="closed">
      <description summary="the overlayed window was closed">
        The window this overlay was attached to was closed, and the overlay
        is no longer shown. The client should
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="commit_before_first_ack" value="0"
        summary="surface committed before first ack_configure request"/>
      <entry name="dimensions_mismatch" value="1"
        summary="failed to match width or height of configure event"/>
      <entry name="invalid_serial" value="2"
        summary="serial provided in ack_configure is invalid"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <description summary="ack a configure event">
        When a configure event is received, once the client commits the surface
        in response, the client must make an ack_configure request before the
        commit request, passing along the serial of the configure event.

        If the client receives multiple configure events before it can
        respond to one, it only has to ack the last configure event.

        A client is not required to commit immediately after sending an
        ack_configure request - it may even ack_configure several times
        before its next surface commit.

        A client may send multiple ack_configure requests before committing,
        but only the last request sent before a commit indicates which
        configure event the client really is responding to.

        Sending an ack_configure request consumes the configure event
        referenced by the given serial, as well as all older configure events
        sent on this object.

        It is a protocol error to issue multiple ack_configure requests
        referencing the same configure event or to issue an ack_configure
        request referencing a configure event older than the last configure
        event acked for a given lock surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial from the configure event"/>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="the client should resize its surface">
        This event is sent once on binding the interface and may be sent again
        at the compositor's discretion, for example if the overlayed window
        is resized. The client should respond as soon as possible with the
        ack_configure request and matching commit.

        The width and height are in surface-local coordinates and are exact
        requirements. Failing to match these surface dimensions in the next
        commit after acking a configure is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial for use in ack_configure"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
